Guide to the Collection of Bookplates by Robert Osmond
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of bookplates by Robert Osmond
1898-1961
1900-1930
BKP 130
Yale University Arts Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection contains bookplates by the English engraver Robert Osmond (1874-1959).
Osmond, Robert, 1874-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from John Rutherford Osmond, 1960.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Osmond (1874-1959) was born in Islington, North London. At the age of 14, he was apprenticed to the engraver William R. Corke, whose gold- and silversmith business was located in Northampton Square, Clerkenwell. Osmond received numerous awards for his designs and engravings, which Corke had submitted to exhibitions and competitions. After a seven-year apprenticeship, Osmond headed the engraving branch of W. R. Corke located in the West End of London.
In 1905 Osmond began designing and engraving bookplates for John & Edward Bumpus Ltd. He eventually left Corke and set up his own business on nearby Warwick Street. William Phillips Barrett (1861-1938) was also an employee of Bumpus, but Barrett was responsible for bookplate orders rather than the engraving. Nevertheless, Barrett's initials appear on hundreds of bookplate designs produced by the Bumpus firm. Many of the W.P.B. designs may in fact be the work of Osmond or other engravers associated with Bumpus (including J.A.C. Harrison, John Edward Syson, Charles Bird, and George Ernest Vize). By 1910, Osmond seems to have been the exclusive in-house engraver for Bumpus bookplates. He had a long and prolific career, including numerous works exhibited at the Royal Academy.
Reference: Lee, Brian North. Bookplates by Robert Osmond. London: The Bookplate Society, 1998. ALSC Call Number: Z996.O86 L44 1998 (LC)
Scope and Contents
The collection contains bookplates, original sketches, and proofs by the English engraver Robert Osmond (1874-1959). It also includes additional bookplates that may or may not be the work of Osmond as well as some related correspondence and ephemera.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates by Osmond. II. Bookplates by Other Artists. III. Sketches. IV. Correspondence and Ephemera.
Bookplates, British; Bookplates; Correspondence; Sketches; Osmond, Robert, 1874-1959
- Bookplates by Osmond, 1906-1945; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by the patron's last name.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes Osmond bookplates that have been identified in the catalog published by Brian North Lee, Bookplates of Robert Osmond (London: The Bookplate Society, 1998).
  - Adams – Bois, 1906-1927 undated; 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Bookplates for Beckett and Blacker are mounted together.
  - Boldero – Charlton, 1919 undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clerk – Eaton, undated; 14 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Edgar – Fraser, undated; 14 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Garrett – Hambro, undated; 15 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Harmsworth – Kenyon, 1923 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kaye – Macneill, 1928 undated; 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Bookplates for Landauer and Stromberg are mounted together.
  - Mary – Norris, 1906 undated; 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Paget – Sauer, 1920-1945 undated; 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sawbridge – Trotter, 1908 undated; 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tufton – Yorke, 1914 1930 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bookplates by Other Artists, 1898-1927; Series II
  Arranged by artist and then alphabetically by patron's last name.
  This series contains unsigned bookplates as well as those signed by W.P.B., which may in fact have been designed and/or engraved by Osmond.
  - Unsigned bookplates, 1908-1927 undated; 64 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - WPB bookplates, 1898-1907 undated; 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bookplates by other artists, 1907 1922; 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes the bookplate of James Willcox Alsop signed by Alf. J. Downey (1922) and the bookplate of Aug. F. Ammann signed Inv. F.G.H. and J.A.C.H. [John Augustus Charles Harrison] Sc. (1907).
- Sketches, undated; Series III
  This series contains original sketches by Osmond for bookplate designs as well as other vignettes, etc.
  - Sketches, undated; 25 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence and Ephemera, 1906-1961; Series IV
  This series includes autograph and typewritten letters mostly addressed to Osmond, such as requests from bookplate patrons as well as collectors.
  - Correspondence, 1926-1961 undated; 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Arranged chronologically.
  - Ephemera, 1906-1912 undated; 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes examples of other graphic works by Osmond, such as letterhead, genre scenes, etc.